<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo on something bloglike</title>
    <link>http://wbthomason.github.io/blog/tags/hugo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hugo on something bloglike</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 00:26:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wbthomason.github.io/blog/tags/hugo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>init</title>
      <link>http://wbthomason.github.io/blog/post/init/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 00:26:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wbthomason.github.io/blog/post/init/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really bad about actually using my blog. I&#39;ve set it up with at least half a
dozen times, with about three different frameworks, several themes, and once or
twice just because I broke something and it was easier to start over than to fix
things. I&#39;ve had the site up and running for at least three years at this point,
but have yet to publish a single completed post at the time of this
writing.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:partial&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:partial&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I believe that writing regularly is important and beneficial,
particularly for someone in academia.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:hypocrite&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:hypocrite&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As such, and because it&#39;s
about the easiest possible topic for an initial post, this brief post will
detail the process I&#39;ve taken to arrive at the current form of my blog, and what
I intend to do from here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve intended to start things off in several ways over this time &amp;mdash; plans for
posts on programming language design, probabilistic models, and various topics
in mathematics have all been in the works at one time or another. If any of
those had survived the various rewrites I&#39;ve put the blog through, they might be
very well-suited to kickstarting a regular series of informative and interesting
posts. Alas, none did, and so this meager beginning will need to suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:partial&#34;&gt;I did have most of an overview of classical AI written at some point, but deemed finishing the article to be largely pointless.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:partial&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:hypocrite&#34;&gt;In fact, I have the outline of a post about this loitering in some forsaken draft folder somewhere. Once it wouldn&#39;t be hypocritical for me to post it &amp;mdash; i.e. once I actually write regularly &amp;mdash; I intend to flesh it out and publish it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:hypocrite&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>